Arun Kumar UFeatured Resume

HR Manager seeking assignments in HR Management, Administration, Recruitment, Employee Engagement, Talent Acquisition, Training & Development, Manpower Planning, Performance Management, Compensation & Benefits, Organizational Development, Facility Management

Current Designation: HR Manager (Payroll & Compliance)

Current Company: Ecare India Pvt Limited

Current Location: Chennai

Pref. Location: Bengaluru / Bangalore, Chennai, Hyderabad

Functional Area: HR / Administration / IR

Role: HR Manager

Industry: BPO/ITES

Marital Status: Single/unmarried

Total Experience: 12 Year(s) 0 Month(s)

Notice Period: 2 Months

Highest Degree: MBA/PGDM [HR/Industrial Relations]

Key Skills: HR Manager,HR Management,Administration,Recruitment,Employee Engagement,Talent Acquisition,Training & Development,Manpower Planning,Performance Management,Compensation & Benefits,Organizational Development,Facility Management,Industrial Relation

Verified: Phone Number | Email - id

ID: 4e238c2e470b2ccd32Last Active: 17-Sep-20Last Modified: 17-Sep-20

Jump to SectionWork Experience | Education | IT Skills |

Summary

Highly Effective Human Resources Manager with over 12+ years of experience specializing in establishing productive business relationships and resolving critical human capital business issues. Demonstrated competencies in carrying out multiple tasks simultaneously, meeting tight deadlines, maintaining strict confidentiality of company records, coordinating with third parties and surpassing performance parameters. Well-equipped in organizing groups, preparing documentations and reporting. Proactive and efficient team player, sports oriented with excellent analytical, problem solving, organization, coordination, time management, communication and interpersonal skills.

Work Experience

Ecare India Pvt Limited as HR Manager (Payroll & Compliance)

May 2017 to Till Date

Responsible for error free, end to end payroll processing and on-time salary disbursement.

Maintaining payroll information by designing systems, calculation, and entering of data.

Updating payroll records by reviewing and approving changes in exemptions, Employee CTC, Insurance/Mediclaim coverage, savings deductions, job titles, and department/ division transfers.

Paying employees by directing the production and issuance of paychecks or electronic transfers to bank accounts and distributing payslips electronically on timely manner.

Preparing reports by compiling summaries of earnings, taxes, deductions, leave wages and registers.

Preparing thorough workings and remitting employee statutory benefits such as Employee State Insurance Corp (ESI), Provident Fund (PF), Gratuity, Labor Welfare Fund (LWF), Professional Tax (P.Tax) and ensuring with Management for payment closure on timely manner.

Handling compliance administration such as PF Transfer requests, PF claim queries, PF KYC updations, ESI Maternity benefit claims, Death claim process from ESI/PF/Gratuity.

Responsible for maintenance of accurate Payroll Inputs such as Personnel Entry, Separations, Bonus payments, Interim Hikes, Incentive payouts, Salary accounts, leave encashment payouts, deductions.

Determining payroll liabilities by approving the calculation of employee state income and social security taxes, employer's social security, and workers compensation payments.

Hosting and completing Bi-annual Appraisal system, complete Budget workings, Salary grid workings

Designation wise average salary analysis), letter generation and giving effect in Payroll with nil error.

Balancing the payroll accounts by resolving payroll discrepancies.

Providing payroll information by resolving queries.

Maintaining payroll guidelines by writing and updating policies and procedures.

Responsible for Attendance administration and monthly Attendance record keeping for all employees.

Complying with state and local legal requirements by studying existing and new legislation; enforcing adherence to requirements; advising management on needed actions.

Maintaining employee confidence and protecting payroll operations by keeping information confidential.

Maintaining professional and technical knowledge by reviewing professional publications; establishing personal networks; participating in professional societies.

Coordinating with vendor for payroll systems.

HR Manager (Business Partnering)

Second-in-line command for everything related to Human Resource Management of the Organization.

Ensured compliance of Human Resource policy, employee benefits and employment law at all levels.

Managed HR Operations & HR Business Partnering (for both Day & Night business) functions with a team size of 3 & providing adequate mentorship to the Associates consistently.

Provided confidential issue resolution while working with various levels of management.

Advise Managers on Organizational policies and recommend needed changes.

Participating in the Quarterly Management review meetings representing HR Department and working on improvements.

Plan and implement recreational events (monthly fun, yearly cultural & sports events) and budget approvals.

Representing employer in High court, Labor Court, Police Station, Advocates and other Govt bodies as and when required, for handling legal issues.

Being an approved Interview panelist of the Organization, responsible to be a part of IJP and Promotion interviews, analyze and provide recommendations to the Management.

Responsible to conduct orientation to foster positive attitude towards Organizational objectives.

Serve as a link between Management and employees by handling employee issues, incident arise, PIP and serving to resolve work-related problems to foster positive environment.

Responsible for conducting and providing innovative ideas for Rewards & Recognition program on quarterly basis.

Sundaram Business Services Limited as HR Officer

Dec 2013 to May 2017

Consult with line management and provide daily HR guidance.

Resolve complex employee relations issues and address grievances.

Work closely with management and employees to improve work relationships, build morale and increase productivity and retention.

Organizing and conducting induction for new hires, preserving moral and taking care of their welfare.

Responsible for initiation and completion of Performance Management System (PMS)

Handling ISO, ISMS and other internal and external audits.

Responsible for conducting one to one/group connects to understand employees concerns and to recommend organization on possible implementation of changes/improvements.

Responsibility, with the HR department to ensure that all HR policies and procedures are regularly reviewed and continue to reflect both up-to-date employment law and best practice.

Reviewing staff awards processes (R&R) and to design an effective staff award system which recognizes excellent performance.

Conducting retention discussion for resigned personnel to find possible means to retain them.

Provide HR policy guidance.

Identifying training needs for teams and individuals.

Suggest new HR strategies.

Responsible for specific HR related projects from time to time and as required. Researching, progressing and coordinating the project and make recommendations for future actions.

Organizing fun @ work activities.

HR Officer (HR Operations)- Sundaram Business Services Limited

Managed HR Operations function with a team size of 4 & providing adequate mentorship consistently.

Responsible for error free payroll processing and on time salary disbursement.

To coordinate with the finance & MIS department for monthly payroll system, make necessary needful for new joiners, separations, unpaid leave, salary advances, etc. Follow-up with Bank for timely credit of salary & Issuing salary slips.

Preparing complete workings and remitting employee statutory benefits such as Employee State Insurance Corp (ESI), Provident Fund (PF), Gratuity, Labor Welfare Fund (LWF), Professional Tax (P.Tax) and ensuring with Management for payment closure on a timely manner.

Research, implement and administer all company benefit plans.

Maintain all organization policies, procedures and provide guidance and Interpretation to staff.

Ensure all data (new staff, transfers, promotions) and employment changes (Salary changes, separations) are maintained for two group entities of Sundaram Finance which carries employee base of 1000+.

Maintain in-depth knowledge of legal requirements related to HR, reducing legal risks and ensuring all statutory compliance & timely remittances to Govt bodies.

Led the complete migration process from one HRMS system to other which involves payroll, attendance, performance management system, employee self-service etc (Sundaram Business Services).

Maintain employees' attendance in HRMS system and generate attendance reports to stake holders as and when required and for salary processing.

Develop and maintain Human Resources systems that meet HR personnel information needs.

Consult with line management providing HR guidance when appropriate.

Identifying training needs for HR Operations team and individuals.

To maintain personnel dossier for complete employee life cycle.

To take responsibility for specific HR related projects from time to time and as required. Researching, progressing and coordinating the project and make recommendations for future action.

WNS Global Services as HR Executive

Mar 2012 to Dec 2013

Validate employees' documents, bank account opening and present company policies.

Conducting Induction program for all new hires.

Generate Employee ID's and improve processes based on GAP analysis report.

Record complete life-cycle of the employee using HRMS PeopleSoft.

Identify the requirements from business and process as per policy and procedures of IJP; Plan the IJP calendar in correlation with IJP team and arrange for Competency Based Interviews (CBI) panel for interviews.

Conducts exit interviews, promotion and progression exercise for all job levels in unit and Resource management.

^ Back to Top

Education

UG: B.Com (Commerce) from Madras University in 2008

PG: MBA/PGDM (HR/Industrial Relations) from Pondicherry University in 2014

^ Back to Top

IT Skills

Skill Name Version Last Used Experience

People vision, Oracle HRMS PeopleSoft

Ramco Virtual works, Formula HR

Applecart/Cpay V7 & V10

MS OFFICE